Dr.Patrick J. Nicholson Papers, 1933-1979
University of Houston Libraries
- University of Houston (Box 15-18)
  - Development (Box 15, Folder 23-25)
    - Proposed Development Brochure, 1956 (Box 15, Folder 24)
    - Proposed Development Brochure, undated (Box 15, Folder 25)
  - Teaching (Box 16, Folder 1-4)
    - Teaching Management 335, 1952-1959 (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Teaching Materials Management 335, 1954-1959 (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - Class notes Management 335, undated (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - Teaching Psychology Class Notes, undated (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Subject Files (Box 16-18)
    - Agenda: Regents Invitational Dinner, 1955 (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - Associates-Individuals Recommended by Regents, 1955 (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - Public Relations Courses in Schools and Departments of Journalism, 1955 (Box 16, Folder 7)
    - Service Proposal to Reed Roller Bit Company, 1956 (Box 16, Folder 8)
    - Acta Diurna, 1957 (Box 16, Folder 9)
    - Ford Foundation Grant Proposal, 1958 (Box 16, Folder 10)
    - Research and Ph.D. Programs, 1953-1959 (Box 16, Folder 11)
    - Faculty and Staff Handbook, 1959-1960 (Box 16, Folder 12)
    - University of Houston: A Study of Administrative Management, 1960 (Box 16, Folder 13)
    - Report to the General Faculty Meeting Vice President's Remarks, 1961 (Box 16, Folder 14)
    - Dr. Philip G. Hoffman, Vice President of Academic Affairs, Dean of Faculties, 1957-1961 (Box 16, Folder 15)
    - Inauguration of President Hoffman, April 27 1962 (Box 16, Folder 16)
    - Memorial Service for the Late President of The United States, John Fitzgerald Kennedy, 1963 (Box 16, Folder 17)
    - Creative Thinking Correspondence Only, 1957-1963 (Box 16, Folder 18)
    - Creativity Research Exchange, 1961-1963 (Box 16, Folder 19)
    - Gonser and Gerber Bulletin, 1954-1964 (Box 16, Folder 20)
    - Gonser and Gerber Bulletin, 1965-1969 (Box 16, Folder 21)
    - Lamar Fleming Building Dedication, 1965 (Box 16, Folder 22)
    - Study of Texas College and University Libraries, 1967 (Box 16, Folder 23)
    - Afro-American Programs, 1968-1969 (Box 16, Folder 24)
    - AABL: Restraining Order, Temporary Injunction vs Mark Rudd and Marjorie Ellen Davis Haile, 1969 (Box 16, Folder 25)
    - A-ABL: 1 Afro-Americans for Black Liberation, 1969 (Box 16, Folder 26)
    - Arts on Campus, 1969 (Box 16, Folder 27)
    - Black Mass, 1966-1969 (Box 16, Folder 28)
    - Gerry Charlotte Phelps, 1969-1970 (Box 16, Folder 29)
    - Excellence Campaign Comparative Report and 1969-1974 Comparison of Unrestricted Dollars Raised, 1970-1974 (Box 16, Folder 30)
    - Association of American Colleges Annual Meetings, 1970 (Box 16, Folder 31)
    - Cameron Building Dedication, 1970 (Box 16, Folder 32)
    - Chapman Case, 1970 (Box 16, Folder 33)
    - Tree Controversy, 1970 (Box 16, Folder 34)
    - Tree Controversy Articles, 1970 (Box 16, Folder 35)
    - Governor Preston Smith Campus Visit, 1970 (Box 16, Folder 36)
    - A Decade of Progress, 1961-1971 (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - Advertising Daily Cougar, 1972 (Box 17, Folder 2)
    - The New Campus, 1972-1973 (Box 17, Folder 3)
    - U of H Miscellaneous, 1972-1973 (Box 17, Folder 4)
    - Area Information Officers, 1973 (Box 17, Folder 5)
    - Journalism Assembly, 1973 (Box 17, Folder 6)
    - Journalism History, 1973-1974 (Box 17, Folder 7)
    - Energy Institute, 1973-1974 (Box 17, Folder 8)
    - The Energy Institute and Energy Research at the University of Houston, 1974 (Box 17, Folder 9)
    - Advertising for Continuing Education, 1974 (Box 17, Folder 10)
    - Ruth S. Wikoff, 1974 (Box 17, Folder 11)
    - President Philip G. Hoffman Commencement Address: UH/VC, 1975 (Box 17, Folder 12)
    - Commencement Convocation of UH Downtown, 1976 (Box 17, Folder 13)
    - Legislative Appropriations Reference Book (Box 17, Folder 14-16)
      - 1 of 3, 1976 (Box 17, Folder 14)
      - 2 of 3, 1976 (Box 17, Folder 15)
      - 3 of 3, 1976 (Box 17, Folder 16)
    - Remarks by Philip G. Hoffman before the Committee on Program Development Coordinating Board, 1976 (Box 17, Folder 17)
    - Report on Departmental Analysis, 1976 (Box 17, Folder 18)
    - Sports, 1976 (Box 17, Folder 19)
    - 50 Fund Material (Box 17, Folder 20-23)
      - folder 1 of 4, 1976 (Box 17, Folder 20)
      - folder 2 of 4, 1976 (Box 17, Folder 21)
      - folder 3 of 4, 1976 (Box 17, Folder 22)
      - folder 4 of 4, 1976 (Box 17, Folder 23)
    - Printing-General, 1974-1976 (Box 17, Folder 24)
    - Manual of the Board of Regents, 1976 (Box 17, Folder 25)
    - The Story of Texasgulf by Dr. Charles F. Fogarty, 1976 (Box 17, Folder 26)
    - Basic Data, 1974-1976 (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - Basic Data, undated (Box 18, Folder 2)
    - Tex-Pirg, 1972-1977 (Box 18, Folder 3)
    - Page proofs, marked for indexing, 1977 (Box 18, Folder 4)
    - Report: Remarks by President Hoffman before the House Appropriations Commission (Box 18, Folder 5-6)
      - folder 1 of 2, 1977 (Box 18, Folder 5)
      - folder 2 of 2, 1977 (Box 18, Folder 6)
    - UH50 Fund, 1977 (Box 18, Folder 7)
    - Testimony Before House of Representatives, Higher Education Commission, 1978 (Box 18, Folder 8)
    - Presidential Commission on Academic Priorities in the Arts and Sciences, Columbia University (Box 18, Folder 9-10)
      - folder 1 of 2, 1979 (Box 18, Folder 9)
      - folder 2 of 2, 1979 (Box 18, Folder 10)
    - Central Campus Organization, undated (Box 18, Folder 11)
    - Controversy U.H., undated (Box 18, Folder 12)
    - Photographs of Campus, undated (Box 18, Folder 13)
- Personal (Box 19, Folder 1-18)
  This series consists mainly of brochures, invitations and Christmas cards, which do not relate to the University of Houston. They have been maintained with the collection to give the researcher a more complete perspective on Nicholson's life. The folder entitled "Hitler Wager" contains correspondence between Leopold L. Meyer, of Foley Brother's Dry Goods Company, and H.R. Cullen concerning a wager between the two men. Additional topics include organizations and clubs with which Nicholson was involved, including the Hibernians and Allegro. The Hibernians are an Irish Catholic organization dedicated to the protection of "American democracy, liberty of conscience and freedom of religion," and Allegro was an organization that sponsored a debutante ball each year. This series is arranged chronologically.
  - Hitler Wager, 1943-1944 (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - The Playbill, 1953 (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Brochures, 1958 (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Saint Michael's Parish, Roster, 1959 (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Dissertation: An Experimental Investigation of the Effects of Training Upon Creativity, 1959 (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1946-1959 (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - Social: Center Club of Hotel America, 1963 (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - PJN-Personal Cork Club, 1961-1965 (Box 19, Folder 8)
  - Headliners Club, 1966 (Box 19, Folder 9)
  - Allegro, 1958-1966 (Box 19, Folder 10)
  - Houston Country Club, 1957-1968 (Box 19, Folder 11)
  - Religious, 1960-1968 (Box 19, Folder 12)
  - Houston Division of the Ancient Order of Hibernians in America, 1964-1968 (Box 19, Folder 13)
  - Criterion Club, 1966-1968 (Box 19, Folder 14)
  - Brochure: Modern Values In Politics: Women And The Labor Movement, 1975 (Box 19, Folder 15)
  - Personal, Invitations Received, undated (Box 19, Folder 16)
  - Christmas Cards, undated (Box 19, Folder 17)
  - Metropolitan Opera, undated (Box 19, Folder 18)
- Oversized (Box 20-21)
  This series contains extensive newspaper articles relating to both university and non-university issues. The university topics include Texas Governor Smith's 1970 visit, university sports, the university in general and early university history. The newspaper articles relating to non-university topics include additional materials on the Hibernians and Allegro.
  - University of Houston (Box 20, Folder 1-4)
    - Early University of Houston, 1933-1947 (Box 20, Folder 1)
    - Miscellaneous University of Houston, 1953-1976 (Box 20, Folder 2)
    - University of Houston Sports, 1968-1978 (Box 20, Folder 3)
    - Governor Smith Visit Newspaper Articles, 1970 (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - Personal (Box 21, Folder 1-3)
    - Allegro Debutantes, 1957-1966 (Box 21, Folder 1)
    - Hibernians, 1968 (Box 21, Folder 2)
    - Miscellaneous, Dates Vary (Box 21, Folder 3)